Lorenzo Fabbri

Summary

I am a PhD student at the Barcelona Institute for Global Health (ISGlobal). I work under the supervision of Prof. Martine Vrijheid. My main topic of interest is the use of modern Causal Inference methods to answer questions in the broad field of Environmental Neuroepidemiology. I am also profoundly interested in Open Science and Reproducible Research.

I received my Bachelor's degree in Biotechnology and my Master's degree in Quantitative and Computational Biology. My personal webpage can be found here. You can also find me on Bluesky and GitHub.

Working Experience

PhD Student Barcelona Institute for Global Health (Barcelona, ES)	2021 - Present
Student Research Assistant Fellowship Università della Svizzera italiana (Lugano, CH)	2017 - 2017
Funding	
ATHLETE Fellowship Programme ATHLETE (Barcelona, ES)	2024
Meritatamente 2023 Società Unione Mutuo Soccorso (San Marino, SM)	2024
Meritatamente 2022 Società Unione Mutuo Soccorso (San Marino, SM)	2022
Erasmus+ Traineeship Programme Scholarship University of Trento (Trento, IT)	2019
Faculty of Informatics Scholarship Università della Svizzera italiana (Lugano, CH)	2016
Erasmus Traineeship Programme Scholarship University of Parma (Parma, IT)	2015
Honors and Awards	
Outstanding Abstract by a Student International Society for Environmental Epidemiology	2022

Publications

My ORCiD is 0000-0003-3031-322X.

- 1. **Fabbri L**, Garlantézec R, Audouze K, et al. Childhood exposure to non-persistent endocrine disrupting chemicals and multi-omic profiles: A panel study. *Environment International*. Published online February 26, 2023:107856. doi:10.1016/j.envint.2023.107856
- 2. Thiel C, Cordes H, **Fabbri L**, et al. A Comparative Analysis of Drug-Induced Hepatotoxicity in Clinically Relevant Situations. *PLOS Computational Biology*. 2017;13(2):e1005280. doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005280

Conference Presentations

The posters can be found here.

Childhood exposure to non-persistent endocrine disrupting chemicals and multi-omic profiles: a panel study ISEE Annual Conference, Athens (GR)

2022

Childhood exposure to non-persistent endocrine disrupting chemicals and multi-omic markers in a population-based child cohort

EURION Cluster Annual Meeting (online)

2022

Childhood exposure to non-persistent endocrine disrupting chemicals and multi-omic markers in a population-based child cohort

International Prenatal Programing and Toxicity Meeting (online)

2022

Efficient and Portable MPI Support for Approximate Bayesian Computation

Platform for Advanced Scientific Computing Conference, Lugano (CH)

2017

Education

PhD Programme in Biomedicine

Universitat Pompeu Fabra (Barcelona, ES)

2021 - Present

- Supervisor: Prof. Martine Vrijheid.

M.Sc. in Quantitative and Computational Biology

Università degli Studi di Trento (Trento, IT)

2017 - 2019

- Thesis (FBK, Trento (IT)): Machine Learning for Predictive Drug Induced Hepatotoxicity. Supervised by: Dr. Cesare Furlanello, Dr. Marco Chierici, Prof. Enrico Domenici.
- Internship (HITS, Heidelberg (DE)): Machine and Deep Learning for Predictive Unbinding Kinetics of Kinases. Supervised by: Prof. Rebecca Wade, Dr. Daria Kokh, Prof. Raffaello Potestio.
- Final mark: 110/110 With Honors.

M.Sc. Student in Computational Science

Università della Svizzera italiana (Lugano, CH)

2016 - 2017

- Project (USI, Lugano (CH)): Investigation by Computational Techniques of Channelopaties related to Sodium Channels. Supervised by: Prof. Vittorio Limongelli, Prof. Daniele Di Marino.

B.Sc. in Biotechnology

University of Parma (Parma, IT)

2012 - 2016

Sep 2017

Jul 2017

- Thesis (RWTH, Aachen (DE)): Whole Body PBPK Modeling of Valproic Acid. Supervised by: Prof. Elena Maestri, Prof. Lars M. Blank, Dr. Henrik Cordes.
- Final mark: 103/110.

University of Wurzburg, Wurzburg (DE)

CSCS and University of Lugano, Lugano (CH)

Effective High Performance Computing Summer School

Continuing Education	
Spring School in Causal Inference with Observational Data Causal Insights, Leeds (UK)	Apr 2022
Computational Bayesian methods using brms in R Physalia Courses, online	Feb 2022
ELIXIR Omics Integration and Systems Biology National Bioinformatics Infrastructure Sweden, online	Sep 2021
Fundamentals of Epidemiology (EPM101) LSHTM, online	Sep 2021
Advanced Statistics: Statistical Modelling Swiss Institute of Bioinformatics, online	Aug 2021
Alpine Exposome Summer School Inserm and ATHLETE, online	Jun 2021
Metabolomics Data Processing and Data Analysis University of Birmingham, online	Feb 2021
Mendelian Randomisation Imperial College London, online	May 2020
Image Analysis and Modeling of Complex Biological Dynamics	

MARVEL School on Variationally Enhanced Sampling

University of Lugano, Lugano (CH) Feb 2017

Advanced Course in Alternatives to Animal Experimentation

University of Genova, Genoa (IT)

Nov 2015

Service

Students and New Researchers Network

International Society for Environmental Epidemiology 2022 - 2023

Early Career Scientist Working Group

COnsortium of METabolomics Studies 2022 - 2022

Skills

Languages Italian (native), English (C1, IELTS 7.0), Spanish

(basic)

Programming Languages R, Python, MATLAB, C

Markup Languages LaTeX, RMarkdown

Software Development git, SLURM, High Performance Scientific Computing